hello everyone and welcome back to
active inference insights I'm your host
darus P way and today I feel extremely
lucky to be able to interview two
exceptional researchers Dr Michael Levan
is a distinguished professor of biology
at T University serving as director of
the Allen Discovery Center at tus and
the tus Center for regenerative and
developmental biology his lab studies
anatomical and behavioral decision-
making at multiple scales of biological
artificial and hybrid systems fr
cookling is Mike's postto at toughs with
a special interest in the physics of
life and how cells adapt to changes in
their physical environment guys welcome
to the show thank you so much for
joining me it's an absolute pleasure and
an honor um you're kind of you know
everyone in active inference has a foray
into theoretical biology but I would say
you guys are the first out andout
biologist that we've had on the show so
I'm super excited to learn um but you
may have to excuse some of my more
Layman ideas that come from the British
schooling system where I wanted to start
is probably just putting in some
groundwork for the audience uh who might
be unaware of certain terms that get
used in in the papers that you guys
write I wanted to start with
morphogenesis what is
morphogenesis and in what kind of you
talk about moros space what is moros
space and how do those two things relate
yeah I don't know who want to take it I
guess I I'll start and and then France
can give his view um so so thanks for
having us um it's a pleasure to to be
here and to talk to you um uh there
there's a there's a fundamental fact of
biology which is that uh complex shape
and and functional structure are
self-assembled so uh let's just think
about embryonic development we all Start
Life as a single cell and eventually
that single cell has to give rise to a a
a complex organism of different types
and so this not only during development
but also during regeneration so for
example a salamander loses a limb those
cells have to not only uh restore the
entire structure but then also know to
stop when it's done okay and uh there
are other examples of this of course
metamorphosis when caterpillar gets to a
butterfly or or something like that so
there there are numerous examples where
the
biological Hardware is uh is is
basically reconstructing itself and so
this is broadly conceived this is the
notion of morphogenesis now one way to
look at this is as a sort of open loop
process meaning that there are a set of
rules that are executed and parallel so
um lots of molecule cells and so on are
are following these rules and then uh
there's a process of emergence and
something complex comes out the other
end you know this is the standard story
of cellular atoma or other ways to think
about emergent complexity and that's
true I mean that does happen and that's
certainly part of the story but the more
interesting part of the story is that
morphogenesis whether developmental
regenerative or in the context of cancer
suppression or remodeling any of those
kinds of um examples one of the amazing
things that it can do is get to its get
to its Target morphology despite various
perturbations so if you want to dig in
I'll give you I can give you all kinds
of interesting examples where not only
the environment changes not only injury
but actually the components themselves
the the amount of DNA the type of DNA
the number of cells the size of cells
all of these things can change and
certain morphogenetic systems are
amazing at getting where they're going
despite all of these things in fact they
will often take U novel paths to do it
which is uh William james' definition of
intelligence right same goal by
different means so um one way to so so
so then so then the question is what
what conceptual tools can we bring to
bear to understand this process uh and
what we have settled on or or at least
what what we've been we've been uh
pursuing for the last some some years is
this idea of navigation that what's
actually happening here is that you have
a collective intelligence it's basically
a set of processes um hierarchically
organized from molecules to cells to
tissues and so on and what they're all
doing is navigating the space of all
possible outcomes so there's a there's a
huge um you know space of of diverse
morphologies that they can achieve and
what they're doing is like any agent
navigating its environment they are they
are trying to get to where they're going
and sometimes they have interesting
competencies to do it even when things
go wrong so now we can bring to bear all
of the tools of behavior science of of
control theory all this you know
cybernetics all the stuff that's used to
design um autonomous vehicles you know
all of these kinds of things to ask how
does the system know where it is how
does it remember where it's going and
what competencies does it have to get
there so that's that's that's why we use
the notion of morphospace because it
allows us to make testable specific
hypotheses about the policies that that
are involved in this process wonderful
that's a that's a really nice background
from which we can kind of explore these
ideas yeah it seems when you put it that
way very consonant with the the ideas of
Act of inference which is obviously
something that you guys have have
written about before so friend maybe
I'll come to you
now you there's this idea in these so so
people think of priors in sort of
statistical space or more broadly about
the organism as a whole you know what
are the priors of the organism to be
welfare to eat and so on but we could
also talk about a cell's prior or an a
cell's posterior and basian unfolding
basian processes within the cell what in
this idea of navigation and self
organization what would you say the
cells prior is is it purely to reach a
kind of Target morphology or is there
anything more than
that I would say there's a lot more than
that but that's the most um the simplest
to kind of formulate because morphos
space like Mike was um explaining is
something that we we have much more
access to as a development of biologist
right so the the challenge is you can
formulate all kinds of Prior and belief
expectations for your but if you have no
way to to estimating how that's even
being achieved and that's hard to really
um put in any theory that that's you
know experimentally accessible but for
one thing kind to point out that the
idea of a morphospace or cells
navigating uh spaces is is only
challenging for for people that not in
involved in this field because we so
used in spatial Dimension as that being
the space right but you can assign all
kinds of Dimensions to to a cell we do
this for humans all the time you know
the idea of of characters in in a plot
being multidimensional is something that
is very much applicable to celles as
well so to ask to answer your question
more recently so what what happens in
terms of expectations of a cell it might
have you have to really go into what is
it constantly achieving has any
relevance for future States so that's La
is can be transcriptional States so what
kind of genes are being expressed at any
point in time and that is being informed
not just by the by the structure of the
DNA so by millions of years of evolution
it's also been formed by past um events
not just in in that individual cell but
in it parent cells and and and going on
so that's what we call the epigenetic
landscape so which genes are actually
even accessible for the transcription
machinery and which genes are being
activated to really transcribe and make
certain proteins down the line and so
that really is something where where a
lot of the pr expectations are going
into um that we at least now in the lab
are really investigating of what kind of
transcription profiles do we see but
then also in terms of this it's membrane
potential you know and lab studies bi
potentials a lot that's something that
of course for Neuroscience much more
familiar we talk a lot about Action
potentials we don't have those in in
non- neuronal cells but every cell has a
has a m potential electric potential and
those are informative and they are um
causing lot of Downstream events so we
can get more downt online but that's
part of what I think is um part the PRI
belief and expectations that sell is
constantly having excellent yeah um I
think there's a really important point
there which is kind of something that I
noticed reading your papers which is
that morphogenesis the the the very idea
of physical space seems to be
prioritized um it's self-organization in
space is that the only way just in terms
of conceptualization is that the only
way that we could think of a cell you
know reaching a posterior that aligns of
its prior does it have to be in
accordance with some kind of
self-organization space or is there
another way that a cell could kind of
reach a homeostatic set
point I'm absolutely it doesn't have to
be just space right so um even if you
have a cell just somewhere in the body
already differentiated already kind of
has it morphology achieved it has to
maintain that morphology first of all
but then also it has to perform a
certain function right your kidneys
cells your liver cells they have very
different functions even though they're
all fixed in space and physical space so
PRI beliefs are you know in this case
for example for kidney cell is what kind
of um what kind of um changes in the
blood are being am I being exposed to
Parts in the liver same thing um if you
have cells in in the brain why it's
different they have expectations about
Action potentials so um it that space
right and again morphos space isn't just
um spatial Dimension right it's also
it's also traversing because every cell
body this an important point every cell
in your body has exact same DNA more or
less right but what's actually being
expressed that's the the difference
between all of them so they are vastly
different in the actual proteins but
also in the genes are being expressed
constantly so when we say traversing and
navigating the morphos space we really
talk a lot not just about that physical
space but how are they changing which
genes are being expressed between being
turn on and off which really makes the
cell identity in the end excellent yeah
yeah that that's that's absolutely
really really useful to integrate
function and space there and I guess
those two they feel to me inextricable
but actually perhaps so I'm wrong there
Mike is it how so so reading kind of the
active inflence account of morphogenesis
we talk about the external states of the
mark of blanket for a cell being other
cells and in the case of Developmental
processes you it turns they end up being
other specific type of cells that they
then join together with in morphos space
is that how how necessary is the
presence of specific other cells in the
basian unfold for a particular cell or
could you imagine that a cell's prior
might be
confirmed you know absent a specific
collection of external
cells yeah I mean this is this is a
great question and it's it's part of a
very emerging research program because
it really isn't super clear uh yet uh
what precisely cells are paying
attention to and and what their internal
models of the outside world are what we
do know is that in for examp example
let's just take let's just take early
development so you have a blastoderm and
there are I don't know 50,000 cells
there and at some point we as as
external observers will'll look at that
and we'll say well there's an embryo
there's one embryo well what is there
one of right and and if you if you want
to think about an embryo the thing
you're really counting when you say one
is you're counting the fact that all of
the cells have bought into the same
picture of the outside world and what
their goal is so so they are all going
to cooperate to build a particular thing
what binds them together into being one
larger scale emergent individual is
commitment to a particular model of of
what where where they um where they
belong where the boundary is between
them and and some other embryo opar
because you can you can make by putting
in little little scratches into that
blastoderm you can make twins triplets
you know there are multiple individuals
that can come from that Blaster so every
cell um has to be part of some in in
that scenario has to be part of some
Network and that network has to make
decisions about where it ends and where
the outside world begins because that
has to do with size control and and you
know Left Right asymmetry and all kinds
of things so uh it's really critical to
understand what exactly um the the cells
are paying attention to what exactly the
uh tissue is paying attention to so the
cell network because I actually think
that there are uh there are agents here
at every level so even actually even to
take a step back you know um even
molecular networks within cells I don't
even think you have to get to the to the
level of a cell before you can start
talking about um beliefs and and
expectations and so on because as we see
even Gene regulatory networks can learn
from experience they they can do
something like five or six different
kinds of learning including pavlovian
conditioning and so you can you can ask
that question about what does the world
look like from the perspective of a gene
regulatory Network before it's been
trained or after it's been trained and
so on right so this is all of course
very very active uh areas of
Investigation still so we don't know all
the answers but but I think I think it's
very important to start taking the
perspective of the things that we are
modeling and asking what do they see and
what what are they measure ing what are
they paying attention to how do they
remap information into Salient um
compressions for them you know and and
and how that affects decision- making
and so on how does that then um
integrate with a kind of idea of Telos
or tonomy um because you know the way
you if we take the perspective of a cell
or a collection of cells that are
parametrizing beliefs over external
States it sounds purposive it sounds
like as you say there's agency there um
and even the word beliefs people
associate with propositional
philosophical
beliefs how far should we take that
metaphor
literally well okay so so the first
thing I would say about that is just as
kind of a ground ground rules I I don't
believe in the dichotomy of literally
versus metaphorically okay I think all
we have in science is metaphor and and
and what what you know when people talk
about molecular Pathways I mean talk
about a metaphor right the pathway
relative to what's actually going I mean
this is completely metaphorical so all
of all of these things are metaphors the
real the real question of course is what
set of tools does that metaphor give you
to make progress what does it help you
discover what does it facilitate so uh
to me all of this is gets settled
empirically to the to the uh to the
point that uh if if you have a
particular metaphor so maybe you talk
about cells as having beliefs or maybe
you don't and the real question is what
does that worldview allow you to do and
I think that's the final judge of it I
don't I don't really put a lot of weight
into sort of philosophical
pre-commitments about what what goals
and beliefs have to be it's a question
of to Port portability of tools so um I
now now having said that so so I think
that uh these kind of um uh these kind
of tools are extremely useful and
they're again not binary because even
even as early as the 40s already uh uh
weer Rosen Bluth and Bigalow gave us a
um kind of a scale of different types of
different goals of different complexity
right so it's so very simple kinds of
passive matter and then active matter
and then and homeostat various kinds of
homeostats and second order
metacognition and so you can you can
sort of go up and up and and it's an
empirical question which of these are
the most useful for any of the contexts
that you study but I think it is uh it
is absolutely reasonable to see all of
these things as having some position on
that scale and you know it's important
to say that back back before I don't
know let's let's say before the the the
the 30s and 40s
there was a the the problem the problem
with theology was that uh we didn't have
a way of thinking about machines with
goals we sort of Mo most people would
assume that that humans have goals but
other than that we really had no idea
how to cash that out but but it's it's
really critical to to say that we're
past that now we we have a good rigorous
science of uh what it means for for
mechanisms to have goals it's fine it's
not magical anymore we don't have to be
be be afraid of it and um and so uh I
guess guess the last thing I want to say
is the difference between thology and
tonomy so um the def one definition of
tonomy is apparent gold directedness
okay a parent thology and a lot of times
people use that as a kind of um as a
hedge as a way of softening the concept
they say well look it's not real thology
it just looks like Tey you know and and
that's a way so so we don't have to
really um uh commit to be to being teist
we're just going to say just looks that
way so so I like the word tonomy but for
the opposite reason I am not trying to
soften the concept I'm I I I'm you know
not in in in no way uh um kind of
hesitant about using tileology I think
it absolutely Works what I think is uh
useful about the concept of tonomy is
that by putting the word apparent in
there what it does is it focuses on an
observer's point of view apparent to
whom and I think that is a really
critical question to ask in almost all
of the stuff that that we talk about
here which is not some some sort of
objective uh uh Universal uh truth about
these things but from the perspective of
some particular Observer now that might
be a human scientist that might be a
parasite that might be a subcomponent of
the system that might be some sort of
superet of the system that might be the
system itself right we all you know
systems observe themselves too and so so
so what that says is that there is there
is some perspective from which the
system acts as a goal directed agent and
thus that could and then can be can be
used with tools that belong to that so
um that's that's what you know that's
that's what I think is the the most
useful term of uh the sense of tonomy
yeah France I was wondering what you
thought about this because um I think
it's a natural inclination maybe it's a
romantic fiction that we want to ascribe
some teos to smaller let's say or or
less complex entities like cells or
processes within cells there's an
interesting thing that Mike said that I
wanted to pick up on which is that
basically everything in science is a
metaphor I guess where I might slightly
push P back on that is the science of
lived experience um and phenomenology
which we can't help we have to take in
some ways literally because it's the one
thing that we're intimately aware of and
there's a lovely paper by Anthony Jack
and Andreas rof ages ago 2002 I think
where they argue that basically you can
take sort of every psychological
construct and say well every the way
that we you know coales on what
attention means or memory means really
is because of what we how we experience
it
so I was wondering whether there's a
kind of uh tie there I mean or
association between when we talk about a
cell's beliefs a cell's attention a
cell's memory is there any way we can
think of that without bringing in our
own phenomenal
experience it's tough I mean um like
especially initially when I earlier in
my my research when I you know wasn't as
deep into a lot of the the the
metaphysics behind it and all that I try
to really avoid it and I try to really
focus the my audience on on just the
mechanical aspects mechanistic aspects
you know the cell aspects but I found
that it was almost impossible to do that
because all the words we use are so
loaded with everything we have from
psychology um but that being said
nowadays um I I think really the
important part is to do to to do that
transversion transversing those two um
fields and both ways because the the the
claim we're making I think is not that
like a seller is doing the same thing on
the same level on the same scale like
you know Mike really mentioned right
there's there's a certain gradient there
as a as a human being is but we're
trying to understand where the origin of
all these phenomena are coming from and
are there and and more importantly are
the fundamental principles shared
between itself and uh and into more
classical active INF agent like a human
being so things like beliefs right so
when you say that S as a belief people
like oh well you talking about you know
um having religious beliefs and then you
get really fastly trapped into into
these loopholes but I nowadays try to
counter this argument by saying well
what is a belief and like where does it
come from it can't just it has to a
human being has to come from certain
expectations right so you really have to
then go down to how how do you once he
has to Define you have to then go to
some mathematical Frameworks eventually
otherwise it's tough to do without it
and so active inference is nice because
there you have very precise definitions
of what a belief actually is yeah and so
once the kind of trick you can do is
keep a w okay let's talk about Act of
inference human being need you make a
certain process you know you have a
general model General process you define
the mark of blanket so separation
between what's outside that you can't
see and then yourself so an internal
State and then you have a separation of
those two by the active and sensory
inputs you can get right you have
sensory inputs and then you can act upon
the environment to change what those
sensory inputs your eyes your ears are
are perceiving over time that's actually
what agency really is about it's about
controlling you can't really control the
environment if you can't perceive it
what you're actually controlling is how
you perceive the environment but of
course you're doing that by acting on
the environment that's what agency is
sure now once you put it in such a
fastic framework then the I think
transferring that to sales becomes much
more much more easier and much less um
controversial I think yeah I I I sense
that that sort of um less
philosophically Laden more deflationary
account of agency is is definitely
possible it's just control in line with
prior expectations or or you know self
organiz principles of self-organization
I think one thing that perhaps Act of
inference also hasn't got very clear on
but certainly isn't clear in Psychology
is selfhood and in some ways I feel like
it's very fundamental to this question
of morphogenesis and self-organization
in biological space because it's
morphogenesis for who right so likee you
sort of noted that in many way well
we're talking about that we have it's
all Observer relative but also in some
ways it's also internal relative because
they are man you know they are self
organizing for the sake of their own
Integrity so well again that might be
ascribing a Telos that's unwarranted but
it it could be described like that um
what is biological
selfhood and I guess for people who
think of the self as one monolithic
thing how does it how does it be how can
it be distinguished from more complex
forms of selfhood like metacognitive
selfhood or epistemic selfhood and so on
um I think that uh you know the issue of
morphogenesis for whom is actually
really important uh because you know a a
really defective frog embryo might be a
very nice zebra fish embryo and so this
whole right and so and so this whole
notion of You Know M mutation and uh and
just just in general evolutionary change
and what what exactly is a birth defect
is really important and interesting
chemistry doesn't make mistakes so
there's no such thing as as a mistake in
chemistry but there is potentially a
mistake in carrying out developmental
biology depending on what perspective
you're looking at so it's something very
interesting is you know the the ability
to make mistakes is a Hallmark of a
cognitive system right because because
that suggests that you had certain
expectations that were not met and so on
so just the very nature of a of a birth
defect is is interesting so now now the
notion of a self uh I of course there
are many ways to think about it I I'll
give you what how how I've been thinking
about it um what one of the things that
that I really wanted to do uh early on
is to come up with a framework uh to
directly think and compare think about
and compare agents of very diverse
structure and Providence so we're
talking about you know conventional
beings like like us and animals I mean
also those are also of course Collective
intelligences right we're all made of
cells and so on but also you know new
synthetic things that are going to be
created um robots AI hybs h ibds cyborgs
you know all kinds of mixed kinds of
things potential exobiological life and
so on what what do they all have in
common you know what what do all agents
have in common no matter how they're
made and no matter how they got here you
know what their origin story is so what
what I settled on and and so now you see
you know I'm super into the whole
thology thing so so what I settled on is
this notion of um the size of their
goals in other words uh I I Define this
notion of a cognitive likee which is um
it's not the dis that you can sense or
act it's the size of the goals that
you're able to maintain the biggest goal
that you could possibly maintain is the
size of your cognitive likeon so you
know so so every every agent has some
degree of memory going backwards maybe
large maybe small some predictive power
forward and some spatial area of concern
over which its goals play out and um and
so so now now the thing about that is
that that is the the determination of a
cognitive lyone by an observer for
example here you as a scientists are
given a new system you don't really know
how it works and you want to do some
behavioral experiments and you find out
that here are the things that it can
possibly care about that that is a a
third-person investigation of its agency
and we say this is an agent to what what
I think of as a useful definition of the
self is exactly that process in first
person so a self is what how that
process plays out for the system itself
so the system itself also has to be able
to corar grain the outside world and not
only tell agential stories about
um things in its environment that do
things right because no no system can
afford to to track micro States you know
lassus demon isn't going to you you'll
be eaten and and dead long before you
calculate anything so so every every
agent in the real world has to has to
course grain and they they tell these
stories about you know agents other
agents doing things but you also have to
tell that story about yourself to some
extent you you can't avoid it because if
you don't have a compact uh self model
you are not going to be very good at
controlling your own Parts in making
things happen it's just right that's
just part of being effective in the real
world and so I think what we say when we
um what we mean when we say self is the
internal first-person view of a system
about its own right so so so so you so
so there's kind of a bundle of things
you need to have you need to you need to
have a sense of boundary between you and
the outside world so which are the
things that I think are actually me
versus versus not me you need to have
some representation of some space that
you think you're operating in you need
to have some sense of your own sensors
and effectors what what can I actually
do what am I actually sensing and so on
we as third person Observer scientists
uh try to tell those stories about other
things that we work with but but agents
tell them about themselves and so do par
you know parasites and conp specifics
and various you know potential mates and
prey and cheaters and and all these
things everybody's hacking everybody
else and in order to hack other other
agents to hack yourself and your own
parts to have control over your own
Parts requires that sense of selfhood
and it might be you know as as France
said the point isn't to say that every
Rock has human level hopes and dreams
that isn't the point the point is that
uh there there's a huge range in how
much processing is how much sort of meta
processing is done about all of this you
know you can you can roll all this
forward in a in a very kind of minimal
way or you can have all kinds of Loops
where you're actually monitoring your
own progress on certain goals and you
have the ability to change your goals
and to pick new goals I mean there's a
you know you can layer stuff on and on
but that's yeah that's really great
that's a really lovely explanation yeah
it really deeply aligns with the way
that I think about selford which is
fundamentally from a sort of mearian um
phenomenal self- modeling aspect and
that's exactly what Thomas would say
which is that self-modeling is the
capacity to recapitulate or res simulate
the actual data structures of your own
body in a kind of Co grain space so it's
you know the the one thing that came to
mind is talking about the uh cognitive
light cone is in terms of the the extent
of your goal yes it's in space but it's
also in time and that feels like a very
relevant thing here um when I've spoken
to Carl and and when I've seen the
direction of active inference it's very
much going in time uh in in you know the
direction of temporal planning deep
temporal planning which arguably relates
to the depth of your generative
hierarchy because the deeper your
generative hierarchy you know the the
highest levels are going to be tracking
the most invariant and long-term
fluctuations in the external environment
so friend I'm just curious if you're I
mean this is just a thought experiment
is there a way where perhaps if you have
a a cyborg or a tad Pole or you know
some entity that you're examining and
you're trying to get to its cognitive
infrastructure is looking I don't know
whether this would be behaviorally or
anatomically is looking at its capacity
for planning which might well just be
its the depth of its generative
hierarchy does that give us an insight
into its actual
you know existential or or experiential
life I think it does and it relates back
to the your early question about what
are it actual beliefs you know what on
what level are are it belief being
expressed and so I just gave you a
couple examples what I left out is you
know that of course like you just said
what's important is the hierarchy of
that how are these different different
beliefs organized in a certain hierarchy
of of spatial and temporal scale and
also to to I really like the point Mike
earlier by chemistry not making mistakes
right so what that means is the
conclusion of that idea is that any
purely chemical system is not going to
change much it's become entirely
predictable it's not going to push back
on anything in the environment it's
going to have a certain it's going to
come to an equilibrium pretty pretty
fast usually and then that's that's it
and so another way to form this question
of how does a cell how can we um test
agency to answer your question how how
we test um having a sell certain certain
ability to form hierarchy and and form
beliefs we have to understand of how
much push back can it can it give you
can it give to the environment over over
long times and so the way I would probe
this hypothetical cyborg or or tadpole
in terms of like what kind of um
expectations what kind of planning is it
is it doing is you have to really see
how these different parts of that
generative hierarchical model are
interacting so you will have a you have
a quick first response which could be
you know purely physical but then very
often on turns very active in most
system that's the the active inference
part is really what makes life life take
you know it's it is entirely active and
it's active very quickly but also over
long time scales and so um what we're
trying to show in this one paper by
recognition with Chris fields and Mike
was that that's a drive that got
selected for very early on in in
evolution and so the way to Pro the
system is really looking having
different reporters um generically but
also just having certain dies in A
system that will give you readouts of
its its active States like what is it
making what kind Poli is making is it
changing it's l of potential and then
you try to relate those things are they
completely independent are they just you
know a non non living system you expect
those to be pretty pretty static with
certain very predictable Dynamic um
reoccurrences of patterns but in the
living systems they're going to change
and they're going to change dependently
on the scale so one scale is going to
affect the other one and it's going to
continue to doing that and that's I
think how the planning is achieved by
that temporal in uh independent inter
interdependence between those different
aspects of a cell if they were
independent they would be no planning
but if they're dependent of on each
other then the cell is basic going to be
using its long-term processes to
redirect and inform it its active points
at any moment in time nice yeah yeah
yeah and speaks to a kind of almost
predictive coding hierarchy um where you
have these kind of trickle down
predictions Mike did you want to add
yeah just I just want to go back back
for a second to something you said
before which I think is quite
interesting um about the uh the you know
the the the non-metaphorical nature of
our phenomenal experience and I I I I
take your point and I think phenomenal
experience is really important but but
there's there's the issue that we change
right and so and so how you inter so so
I mean for us so let's say puberty is a
is a is an example right where where a
lot of veence changes and things that
you thought were really important
suddenly not important at all but all
this other stuff is now important and
the the example that I really find uh
kind of in meaningful for all this is
the caterpillar to butterfly transition
so what happens there is you've got this
you've got this softbed creature that
has a that lives in a two-dimensional
world and it crawls around and it has a
particular controller for that kind of
soft body you know actuation so it's got
a certain kind of brain and then it has
to be transformed into a completely
different creature that's a hard-bodied
kind of vehicle it flies it lives in a
three-dimensional world and so on and so
so it has a completely different brain
and during that that process the brain
is basically mostly broken down most of
the cells are killed off um and then
reassembled you know it grows it grows a
new brain so so there's there's sort of
three levels of interesting things here
the the first level is that that that
aspect of phenomenal experience like
what's it never mind what's it like to
be a butterfly but what's it like to be
a caterpillar becoming a butterfly and
how much of right and how much of the um
the metaphors that how much of the
things that the caterpillar took very
seriously the butterfly thinks were
total metaphors at this point right if
it could I mean I'm not saying that's
how it thinks about these things but but
right things that were quite um quite
concrete for the for the for the
caterpillar are no longer so for the
butterfly that's the first thing the
second thing is that um we know there's
continuity you know if you if you like
um the stability of memories as a
Criterion for selfhood which a lot of
philosophers like uh we know that the
butterfly remembers things that the
caterpillar learned so there is some
continuity here even though the the
brain cognitive system in the body of
all of that stuff is radically changed
but there's some continuity and so the
next kind of question you think about is
okay where the heck is this memory where
when the that survives total brain re
you know refactoring but the third the
third thing that I find even even more
important about all of this is is comes
from the simple fact that um the way the
way the way they test these memories is
well one one way to do it is you um you
you feed the caterpillar leaves on a
particular color disc and then what you
find is that the so it forms the
Association and then you find that the
butterfly goes back to that disc to feed
right but the but the key the key thing
here is that butterflies and
caterpillars don't eat the same stuff
right the caterpillar eats leaves the
butterfly doesn't care about leaves the
butterfly wants nectar so um so now
something very important you cannot just
you know Persistence of of of the self
in terms of memories what you can't do
is just keep the memories constant
because you'll lose the salience they
make no sense to those memories will
make no sense to the butterfly and in
fact what you have to do something very
interesting you can't learn leaves on
this color you have to generalize to the
to the to the higher category of food
and so right and and and then you have
to remap so this is the part that I'm
super interested about in terms of um
moving memories around and and and
transplants of memories and you know
personal identity and all that you have
to take the the Deep lessons of your
past life and sort of re uh reinterpret
them for your new life which is by the
way completely different anatomy and all
of that but there are some things you
learn that are still pretty useful just
not exactly in the way right it's not
the it's not the details that that
matter now it's the kind of the generic
concept that matters so so re remapping
right remapping that information onto a
new exper onto a a a new um embodiment
for for for that for that being that's
that's why I think the concept of
metaphors is still super strong even for
the phenomenal stuff because because you
can't take any of it literally because
you're not going to be the same later I
mean you know as certainly for some
animals it's more more than so than
others but you you have to understand
the Deep metaphor of what you learn not
the not the specific details of your
experience yes yes that's really good
that's really nice there's a lot there
um yeah it again it's converging with
some of the stuff that I've been
thinking about and writing a little bit
in draft which is I'm kind of I'm coming
to this idea that the self in some ways
is a is a relevance filter a salience
filter such that CU I think at a very
deep phenomenal level everything that
Finds Its way into attention or
awareness is relevant it wouldn't really
make sense and so I I would say that the
one non-metaphorical thing there
although you have the higher order
concept of food is
relevance and relev and meaning making
to me and maybe well I I it's
interesting you say you know we're
trying to go up in abstraction up the
generative hierarchy the one thing that
the butterfly and the Caterpillar share
is the imperative for
nutrition and and maybe that's maybe so
when we can start linking things in some
kind of map of similarity maybe the
thing that unifies them is
preferences um so the caterpillar and
that maybe links us with the caterpillar
and the Butterfly right we have this
unified um goal that said the thing you
said about the fact that they return to
the same kind of leaf is very
interesting because there does seem to
be a idiosyncratic maintenance of memory
uh which I can't quite account for there
it made me think of Andy Clark's paper
um knitting your own Markov blanket
where he talks about the um
metamorphosis of Markov blankets and how
we can kind of get around this problem
of like when is one thing another thing
by adopting a process ontology rather
than a substance ontology but friend or
Mike you know whoever's got an idea on
this is it is it possible it's just a
false move to say that the butterfly and
the caterpillar are the same thing like
that's the same organism we not just say
that you know there actually does become
this division or this separation at and
we it's philosophically vague as to when
it happens but there are you know there
was one thing and then now is
another so so so I think the way uh the
way to avoid these kind of philosophical
traps is by being very practical and
asking why why do you need to know so so
if the right so so if the reason you
need to know is is because you want to
predict how much crawling around there's
going to be then it's absolutely two
different things because there's going
to be zero crawling around afterwards
but if but if what you need but if what
you're trying to predict is um so what
color substrate will it like to feed on
then then then then you need to
understand that it's the same thing
because you will have less predictive
power if you don't understand that it
keeps memories so it's just again I
think we're back to again the the the um
the perspective of of uh you know what
what question are you asking as the
Observer yeah okay cool let's let's park
that there I think something that you've
worked on Mike but also France you
mentioned and I want to pick up on is
the difference between neural and
non-neural
structures um there's a there's a kind
of neural bias in Psychology
Neuroscience a quco bias um France one
why is that the case do you think and
two why should it not be the case if it
should be the case maybe it should be
the case yeah I mean one uh human
Centric because we are humans but more
more fundamentally the reason that that
that we we are so confined on the idea
of of neuros circuits being the only one
that doing any inferences because
they're just very fast right Action
potentials are fast it's a highly
optimal optimized
Network optimized from what right
neurons didn't come from nothing Asos
didn't come from nothing electric
potentials were were being used by cells
way before the U innovation of of
neurons so that is I think the reason
why now we're trying to look at what by
a neural organisms and just cells of of
having these same properties um and more
and I think other than just that being
kind of transition what's also really
interesting is Mike and I both it's one
of my favorite um past daytime
activities is asking neuroscientist what
what about your theory is specific to to
neurons and it's a question that nether
of us has have have gotten a good answer
to yet because a lot of it of course you
know there are certain certain time
periods it takes if you're looking at
fmri Imaging looking at the the
oxygenated blood flow in the brain so
you have to know those those time
constant how fast does it take if you're
looking at if you're actually measuring
act neuron you need to know all these
transition times to really make your
model take but if you change those time
constants and you compensated for that
in your model would still work so as far
as we know um so far we're happy to get
proven wrong on here but so as far as we
know there's nothing that specific about
neurons to that you need to make any of
those models including inflence actually
work they highly optimized and they have
completely different behaviors of course
um because those timings do matter but
they're not necessary for it because
they're not NE they're not incence
framework right it's not necessary to
have a brain to have mof blanket it's
not necessary to have a brain to have
generative model so once all the actual
assumptions that go to a model can be
applied to any Ro systems then you're
good to go and you should apply it to
those systems as well yeah I guess
another biased mapping here is between
cognition and the Brain um and there's I
feel like there's been a a you know a
movement towards obviously in terms of
embodied cognition and the kind of dyn
the agent Arena Dynamic that was
happening but also more recently might
your paper with Anna Ana Chona uh the
brain is not mental you sort of I think
you look at the immune system and sort
of say how the immune system contributes
as well as the neural system in
subserving um adaptive control
self-organization perhaps you could just
speak to that and and say you
know well I mean it's a it's a guess
it's a fault experiment what would it
look like if we didn't have the immune
system if we were just trying to self
organize purely in terms of
neurodynamics yeah um I I mean we
certainly there are uh there are
knockout mice where the immune system is
taken out and all that kind of stuff so
and and and a lot of self-organization
does happen before the immune system
kicks in I think you know I I think the
idea is simply that uh there are many
many different kinds of systems that go
into this Collective that that we see
when we say it's it's it's a human or or
whatever and and all of them are
potentially important contributors to
the to the process um as as France said
you know uh it's it's it's a really
interesting experience to uh to ask
people what a neuron is and and and and
watch them list things that are
basically every cell in the body does
this and and then and then you know so
so I have another thought experiment
that I sometimes do is like like back in
the um you know back in the day when uh
when when the idea of neural networks
was first being worked out right um I
wonder if if if we had come along to uh
to some of the some of the greats uh in
that in that field um and we said uh oh
by the way just just FYI um the
biologist got it wrong thinking is in
the liver not the brain so so there's
two there's two ways they could have
gone right one way is they could have
said I don't care what you say we've got
model of cognition and they require it
to be to be neural so you guys must be
wrong or they could say fine what do we
care are are this what you know the the
the basic calculus of you know mullock
pit all that stuff the basic calculus of
it doesn't require doesn't care what it
is so fine it'll beiver right so so I I
tend to think it would be I tend to
think it would be the latter you know I
don't see really anything in the in the
Deep In The Deep lessons of um
behavioral Neuroscience that's really
about neurons per se you know it's about
multiscale control it's about active
inference it's about all these kind of
deep things that go far beyond brains
and they're applicable to all sorts of
stuff stuff well are there certain
processes which are reserved for the
brain I mean I think someone listening
to this probably a psychologist or a
neuroscientist will say well take the
brain out good luck take the liver out
you know I mean still good luck but you
might have a better chance thinking
right uh for for a short amount of time
I mean take the take the mitochondria
out and uh and and you're done for
pretty much at the same rate as as the
brain now look the bottom line like I
nobody's arguing that the brain isn't
unique and interesting in certain ways
right like we F you know as much as we
find uh protoc cognitive capacities
elsewhere I've never made the claim that
language or longform planning is like
we've not found it could be you know I
wouldn't be terribly shocked if it were
found but but we haven't found it so we
don't make the claim so clearly brains
are interesting and they do they do
interest things but um I think it's
important to
uh make make a distinction between
between having found unique features and
told a very specific predictive story
that that why of why that is versus just
this generic gut feeling that everybody
has that that I have real you know real
feelings and plans and this thing is a
slime mold that I mean I don't know how
many times people have said to me well
that's a slim mold that's not a real
decision it's just physics and and it
just it drives me up a wall because what
do you I mean you don't think we could
tell a physics story about you like of
course we could it wouldn't be a very
good story but but neither is it about
the slime mold and the fact that you can
tell that story doesn't mean anything
there's always a physics story to be
told about anything and so you right I
think I think it's it's fine to have
specific theories about what it is the
brain that's doing differently than
other structures that's great um but a
lot of the resistance to the kind of
Continuum views that that France and I
are talking about comes from a kind of
closet dualism it's people really you
know they just really feel they're
different and and and they have to
accept the fact that the physics are not
different so well now what is it then
right it's like this then then there's
something else and I think not not even
that I'm particularly against that I
just think it should be like come you
know dragged out into the light and
let's just say like say what you think
the difference is you know I think I
think that's really critical see I'm not
sure the difference I'm not sure the
jism really fundamentally is a uh brain
body jism I think it's an awareness body
dualism or Consciousness I mean like a
traditional cartisian dualism I think is
really at play here it's just we're
we've been persuaded that Consciousness
is rooted in the brain and so once you
make that Association then you go well
obviously my brain is special because it
generates Consciousness Consciousness is
special I can in principle imagine
myself being conscious without my liver
my leg my arm and so on and so that's
the special part yeah is am I what am I
missing there no I I think you're right
but but I think I think I think what
people are missing there is when they
say conscious of my liver that isn't
that isn't the question here the
question so so right now your left
hemisphere and my left hemisphere are
having a delightful discussion about why
Lang you know why Consciousness is in
the brain and uh and and how important
the brain is for for Consciousness
that's fine then I will say to and I
don't have a new Theory Of Consciousness
by the way so I'm not like I usually
don't talk about Consciousness at all
but but since we're here I'll I'll just
say that um I I have said that for the
same reasons we think that the brain can
support Consciousness we ought to take
seriously that other parts of bodies
also support Consciousness now at that
point people say exactly what what you
just said which is well I I don't feel
like my liver is conscious but but
that's a huge mistake of course you
don't but you also don't feel that I'm
conscious right that that that's that's
that's exactly right so so so it's nice
that the left hemisphere is eloquent and
it has language and it can tell stories
to to other left hemispheres about how
how you know how conscious it is but
that doesn't mean that what you don't
have spread throughout different regions
of your body is a non-verbal
non-linguistic uh Consciousness that is
not for us to access anym than we can
access each others and that's that's the
you know the fact that you don't feel it
is no surprise there's no surprise there
um you have to take its perspective and
ask what do you think that's going on in
your brain and so so literally um a
student and I have have been uh we have
this um we have this table that that has
rows for the main theories of
Consciousness and for each Theory there
is something specific you know so so so
Stu Hammer off will say it's
microtubules somebody else will say it's
you know electromagnetic field somebody
else will say it's you know integrated
information like what whatever it is and
then and then we just look and say okay
given that where does that occur in the
body and the answer for almost all of
them is everywhere and so none of these
theories as far as I can tell can
distinguish you know uh and then and and
some of them try to rescue it so right
so so IAT has this postulate that says
okay but but but there's there's we're
just going to say there's only one right
that that's that's that's a postulate
you sort of add on to things right
that's not so so that's that's the issue
is that it's not about you feeling your
your liver being conscious it's the
first person perspective which may or
may not be there yeah there's plent to
that I actually yeah I I'm reticent to
dive into Consciousness because all my
podcasts end up being about
Consciousness um and I have biologists
on I don't want you know but yeah it's
it's it's interesting I mean obviously a
lot of this is being we have to take as
a kind of um Axiom that at least for
this conversation that Consciousness is
uh well generated in the brain whether
that's in a property je list or whether
it's in a productive way and I also do
just want to give a shout out to
slightly more esoteric forms of idealism
conscious realism and so on but it also
makes me think about let's if we just
get away from Consciousness in terms of
first person perspective and just talk
about basil intelligence in in in terms
of
morphogenesis it also makes me think
well it's this is a term for
Consciousness but people will talk about
being whether conscious can be is
multiply realizable has multiple
realizability I.E if I put you know you
know CH you know if I had a Chinese
Nation their blocks idea with exactly
the same functions as my brain exactly
the same synapses because there's the
same you know those connections would be
the same between the members of the
Chinese populace and my brain would I
have Consciousness okay if we get away
from consciousness
I guess my question is is morphogenesis
itself can it be is it multiply
realizable in the sense that we're now
talking less about the human body is
there something sort of or and more
towards like cyborgs or robots what you
know people have this intuition I think
as well that there is a life force and a
l vital that leads maybe to this
self-organization right there like
there's got to be something there like
or else why why are these things
resisting entropy why are they
self-organizing and I think the idea is
like well if I just stuck some St of
Prior in a robot why on Earth would that
end up being self like why would that
work to use very reductive language
friend I'm just curious is there like an
added ingredient at least it might be a
metaphor but an added ingredient that we
have to put into a non-carbon based
thing in this case to to give it the
chance to self
organize yeah probably I would if I had
to name be Evol evolvability um that
would be one one part so if if the and
it doesn't have to be evolution of of
its actual physical components that can
be evolution of its of its programming
as well but that would be an important
important point to it
um the one thing I like to point out in
for that question is right I I talked a
lot about in this podcast about one my
one of my biggest interest is really
understanding of where that drive for
for an agency comes from but that's not
just a kind of a philosophical um
interest kind of it's actually really
once once you find sufficient evidence
for that being a fundamental Drive in
evolution then you have to accept the
the to combine that fact with the idea
that well if any part of your body or
any any robot um that you're putting
into this is going to strive to maximize
its agency with respect to its
environment that is the real reason why
if it turns out the liver is not
conscious um right now then the answer
would be if you accept the fact that
well the drive is fundamentally in
evolution any any life system is going
to try to maximize its predictability
and its agency over its environment then
the answer would be well its environment
isn't very interesting so the liver
probably didn't have any any reason to
maximize that drive if you were to put
the liver in or you were to put a robot
into an environment that's very active
very much changing very volatile and you
give it enough either enough time to
evolve if you Comm to vulnerability or
you just put in um a high degree
autonomy over its own beliefs then over
time with that driver it should be able
to to to maximize that the problem right
now is that the way we program robots is
uh is very much right it's it's an very
clear algorithm we don't allow any
adaptiveness to it um and so that's
that's how you would have to go about it
I think and you may not want to do that
just FYI but because the problem right
is um you know we talk about one of my
favorite
um uh examples of why what difference
between machines and and a brain is that
a calculator is infinitely better than
you at calculating you know adding
numbers together multiplying it I mean
you know and it's the dumbest thing ever
like it's so simple and we've had these
things for for decades now but so if you
want to have a predictable reliable
answer it's always correct you know the
the human is not the best best way to do
this that is the reason why we're not
even if we had the theoretical framework
to make a really agentive um intelligent
system um for what we want them to do
which just really make our lives Easier
by making the same thing every day
reliably you wouldn't want to do that
but if your goal was to create a new uh
intelligent um um cognitive agent then
you would have to go about it
differently yes that's an interesting
little Paradox isn't it I mean like the
most robust thing in the world might be
a calculator but it's s quite useless
it's like the more useful you become the
more uh precarious your existences um
Mike I was wondering if you had any
thoughts on that kind of multiple
realizability question and I guess what
I'm going at with that
is it's a very it's a it is a
philosophical question but I think it's
interesting for biologists which is why
would Evol like why would Evolution
prioritize self-organization I mean
there just a fundamental question there
in terms of entropy I mean why do we
have these pockets of neg entropy
entities um is there a biological answer
to that Beyond just well to be a
biological entity you are neg entropy is
is there anything can we get anywhere
beyond that yeah um a couple couple of
things I think are interesting and I
want to be careful here because I I did
I did a little while ago I did um I
started writing a paper on what exactly
is missing from our technology to
provide true agency because I think we
can actually say what some of those
things are and it it quickly sort of
dawned on me that to whatever extent I
was on to something that would actually
lead to a massive creation of of new
beings with that that matter in the
moral sense and not I'm not too
interested in in you know being
responsible for that so some other
people will do it I'm sure but but but
but I don't I don't want to do it so so
so um but but I can but I can say a few
things um I think I think uh when we I I
I when when we make the distinction
between life and Robotics um even aside
from all the hyds and cyborgs that that
show us that it's like a Continuum but
even aside from all that when we make
that distinction here here's what I hear
I think life is what we call things that
are good at scaling up uh goals so so
you know when you have very when you
have a bunch of subunits that have very
basil competencies you know may maybe
all they can do is follow least action
laws or like like really simple
things when when when you've got a pile
of them and the pile has basically
exactly the same cognitive lyone as the
comp the components we say well that's
not living that's a rock that's just you
know but but but life is what we what we
call things where there are um special I
I I've also called it a cognitive glue
there are like these special policies by
which the parts relate to each other
such that the collective has a bigger
cognitive lone in new spaces that the
parts couldn't have and that's and
that's what we call life now now under
that under that way of thinking about it
could you make that out of other things
I'm sure you could and I and you know I
tend to think that in the wide universe
I tend to think that there's probably
lots of extremely diverse examples some
most of which we wouldn't even recognize
of of of that happening and I think um
specifically I think I think what
happens is that uh the The evolutionary
process really I I I don't really think
it makes specific solutions to specific
problems the way that we do when we do
genetic algorithms and things like this
I think what what biological evolution
does is it makes problemsolving machines
and that's because if you overtrain on
your evolutionary priors and you really
take seriously uh what expectations that
you might have about what genes you have
what the environment is like if you take
that too seriously you're done for
because because guaranteed and this is
why I also think that regeneration is
not really about repair of um of
physical damage like like external
damage I think fundamentally
regeneration is about knowing for a fact
that your own parts are going to change
right EV Evolution just means the fact
that you have a so some kind of a
lineage that's subject to mutation
whatever you you know your stuff is
going to change if you don't accept that
you're you're never going to survive
long term so so what ends up Surviving
are architectures that in particular are
these multiscale architectures where the
individual components have agendas and
then this you know they they make up
systems that have other agendas and and
and on and on our our current robotics
by and large is very flat right so you
hope your robot is intelligent but the
but the parts it's made of are not they
don't really tend to do anything on they
don't have their own agendas and I've
given a talk called that why robots
don't get cancer and this is why right
it's because you they're made of parts
that are not that that don't have their
own little little goals in other spaces
and there's no danger of them defecting
unlike biology where it happens all the
time so um I think what's I think what's
happening here is that we end up with
these architectures that uh are by
virtue of cooperation and competition of
parts that that end up being uh being
having a CO a larger cognitive lonee you
end up with this kind of this kind of
intelligence ratchet and we could you
know I could I could tell you stories
about how
that that type of thinking explains you
know planarian the the amazing facts of
planarian regeneration and so on this
this this idea that what evolution I
think really selects for is the
plasticity to and and and and it works
out in different types of animals to
different degrees but but overall the
plasticity to deal with novelty you know
this idea that when you when you emerge
into the uh into the world you don't
know for a fact what you are what you
have is your genome the same as it was
are your cells the rights shape or size
do you have are you in the same
environment you don't know any of these
things you you have to um do your best
in putting together a model of what that
that that's why life is so interoperable
that's why we can make anthr robots and
xenobots and interface living tissue
with crazy nanomaterials and make these
Hots that are you just sort of totally
cobbled together it's because by and
large it's already bought into you know
the the life we see today has already
bought into the fact that um like like
you know everything changes you know and
you and you can't you can't depend on
these things you have to figure them out
in real
time yeah yeah great it you know when
you mention the word cognitive glue it
made me realize that there's one thing
that we haven't even touched upon at all
I haven't even mentioned which is
electricity and
bioelectricity um so I think actually
you had the paper mik didn't you last
year two years ago um about
bioelectricity being the glue of the
cognitive mind soort of from physiology
all the way up to the mind and obviously
this is very much you know a seminal
piece of your work is the processes of
bi bioelectrical processes in cells and
outside of cells in terms of self
organization and I think at least to my
very Layman biological is electricity
almost has the the kind of center of aam
v a kind of thing that you know animates
things and maybe you know I'm thinking
about
Frankenstein um either one of you I
don't mind to everyone
start what you know actually friend it
was something that you mentioned which
is maybe one of these ways that we can
conflate the neural nonneural divid is
the fact that both of them have both of
them fundamentally
electrical what what is it about that
electrical ontology that animates or my
animate intelligence or
morphogenesis so when I was writing my
my PhD thesis I was trying to answer the
introduction the question of where does
where does neuron even come from and the
the best paper I found that was
answering that question was looking into
this very small organism that had just
bunch of vdia around its surface it was
a marine organism that was living on the
bottom of the ocean and it was trying to
Center environments and it by small
changes in electrical fields that that
were happing around it and that was
causing um like many I won't say action
potential but it was causing basically
many vibrations and because us that to
change change his movement so the reason
I think why that would you know why
electricity is that so important here is
just very it's very simple mechanism to
have that is physically a lot more
accessible to all parts of the body
that's actually the primary reason why I
joined Mike laab and why I'm I've become
a biologist I was a physicist before so
I was looking for something in biology
that would be all these would not be
subject to completely different
mechanisms if you switch organisms so
like the moleular pathways we are
typically investigating as biologists
they are of as as they were before they
are now still very important in all
these different functions of the cell
and organisms there kind of somewh
unsatisfactory for the physicist because
it's just so messy right you can't
really make heads or tails of it and
there is no clear field of potential
that is is just one number essentially
right you want to dce it to something
very simple the beauty of using bity is
that's you can you can have one number
one potential you can like a me
potential you describe to cell it's
still made up of all the individual
Parts there's many iron channels
involved in this all the molecular
pathways are still making up they all
feeding into that one um one number that
one B potential but what's more
interesting is the red part right you
saw if you have to constantly compare a
millions of different molecules in a
Cell that's not going a good good
formulation for for achieving
Consciousness for even doing any smart
Behavior having something that you con
constantly having a surface almost like
a space that can read they can write
onto and read out to I think that was
makes electric potential so appealing
that the only question then is like why
wasn't it other physical Fields like
mechanics they are of course very
involved as well in developmental
biology and regeneration as well but
mechanics don't have this neat feature
where it's not as as fast and it's not
as localized so basically the way I see
it the potentials have a have a
beautiful tradeoff between being
physical having a broad readability on
on a cell or even a tissue level but are
confined enough that they can be
modulated enough to actually form active
Behavior which you can't say for most
for the other physical fields that we
would um think about in this context
great Mike you got anything you want to
add
yeah yeah a couple couple of things one
one thing to add is that if if you think
about um one of the really powerful
things about um bioelectricity is that
imagine an ion channel is specifically a
voltage sensitive ION channel so as soon
as Evolution discovers a voltage
sensitive ION channel what you have
there is an element with historicity it
means that uh the current state is a
function of what was going on before and
it means that what you really have is a
voltage gated current conductance AKA a
transistor and so so so you know we know
once you have that then then you can do
anything and so uh electricity is is
really good for these kinds of feedback
loops right both positive and negative
it's good for um representing
information across time and space it's
good for functionally integrating a
system uh across across distance some
some of the um really cool early uh
evolutionary data on this come from
bacterial biofilms and this is um G so's
amazing work uh what basically he's he's
got a paper called them you know
brain-like signaling in bacterial
biofilms and the idea is that already in
a in a mat of bacteria so like a really
long time ago um Evolution
already uh HD onto this uh to this idea
that um by using Electrical uh
electrical signaling to integrate
activity among competent subunits you
can get gains at the collective level so
they take turns it's used for for
nutrient sharing and and and things like
this but but you get these Collective
Dynamics and so I think it's just it's
it's a very convenient modality for it
that was that was found a long time long
before neurons you know picked it up um
it was used for that kind of thing but
but no doubt there are other there are
other ways to do it somewhere out in the
universe there there there's other I'm
sure I'm sure there are other kinds of
cognitive glues out there but but here
electricity works really well cool and
so I know we need to wrap up relatively
soon
um and I guess it's it's a it's a kind
of dark pun but us wrapping up kind of
soon makes me think about aging and
death and Decay and and whatnot and
there's a there's a massive fuss about
aging and Longevity at the moment um and
David Sinclair and this notion of
epigenetic scratches and it kind of
makes me think of the inverse of that
which might be regenerative biology and
the capacity to reestablish
self-organization reestablish uh the
kind of priors that we've been
discussing in terms of the functional
priors the the preference priors the
ones that you know are seeking a certain
sort of uh external state or seeking a
certain probability distribution so as
to be able to fulfill its function so to
speak um
what Mike what is the kind of lay of the
land in your world as to
aging um how seriously should we take
this kind of epigenetic approach I won't
ask about the moral aspect of it because
it's a completely different question
about whether we should live longer or
not
but sure you know having localized uh
morphogenesis and self-organization is
really the currency of biological
systems how viable is it that we can
reest that in something which is you
know where self organization is ailing
and and rather feeble yeah um I think
well the the first thing is I I do just
want to say something about the moral
question because it also gets to the
issue of regenerative medicine more
broadly uh and uh and and Beyond
regenerate medicine human augmentation
and all of these kinds of things so so
the one the one the one thing I want to
uh point out is
uh if it were the case that we were in
some way optimized by some intell
elligence that shared our values then
one could make the argument hey let's
not push too far off of that right
you're you're screwing up the planet and
I get a lot of these emails from people
saying uh well well things are great you
bet you know you scientists better not
mess it up and I just want to be clear
that there there is no basis for for
this for this view we our our life our
health span our aging our susceptibility
to to all kinds of dumb diseases and our
lower back pain and our stigmatism all
this all this stuff is is not in any way
uh o optimized for any of the things we
care about that's just where Evolution
happens to have dropped us off at this
point that's that's it and so there's
nothing magical about this lifespan if
if if you do you know people who are
worried about um augmenting this
lifespan well what if it had been 20 or
30 you know then what and you say well
you know that's too short why is that
too short it could have been anything
it's but my point is it's completely
arbitrary and so and so let's not um
base our decisions about what um what
ought to be on where the process of
random mutation and selection has has
dumped us so that's you know I kind of I
think that's important to say um be be
beyond that I mean we're certainly
involved in uh some some uh some
research on aging and the role of bi
electricity in aging and kind of the uh
uh the degradation of bioelectric
patterning information with age and all
that but I think more importantly is the
my my Weather Vein for all of this stuff
is plaria so so I think you know plaria
basically I think hold hold the answer
to all of life's big questions and so uh
I mean the the asexual form of um
plenaria that we have they do not age
they they they there is no there's no
evidence of an old planarian they simply
they they can go forever so these ideas
that it's some sort of inevitable
accumulation of errors or it's tiir or
it's you know uh clearly there are ways
around it that's the one thing that's we
we have an existence proof uh that uh
and then there's a few other animals
that do but plenaria I think are the
most interesting uh there there is
obviously a strategy that gets around it
and I think it's on us to figure out why
that is and I think it's absolutely not
a coincidence that plener are also
extremely regenerative in addition to
being Immortal they're extremely
regenerative they're cancer resistant
and they have an incredibly noisy genome
because they don't clean their genome in
every generation like we do they right
sematic mutations just if you if it
doesn't kill the cell it just basically
expands into the Next Generation BL can
be mix suppoed every cellet have a
different number of chromosomes they're
just a complete mess and and those are
the animals that are that are highly
regenerative cancer resistant and
Immortal isn't that amazing isn't that
right yeah and and so there so so
finally after after years of being like
feeling scandalized about this you know
the importance of the genome and all
that and and why is the animal with the
with the craziest genome also have all
these amazing capacities um I think we
actually finally have have a a lead on
on what's going on there but um but I
think think I think that's that's what
we need to look at in terms of Aging is
is is I I think if regenerative if the
if the question of regenerative medicine
were solved aging would be solved as a
byproduct excellent yeah I mean it makes
me think
um in some ways I I don't know about the
the function of plaria um you know that
sort of the worms people can search up
pictures of plara um but it makes me
think that they like the in many ways
the there just take ourselves for
example what makes a human a human is in
some ways the fact that the the
preference prior that we have or our
limited functional our functionality is
limited right like I am not going to be
at 39 38 37 and 36 degrees Centigrade
with equal
probability but it sounds to me like
pinaria able to sort of metamorphosize
in some way some of their preferences
because as you say their genome is
shaping is that is that kind of a
misconstrue of what's going on is it
that with or that with the sort of multi
the the multiplicity of the genome the
messy genome comes a multitude of
function or is it that the function is
still
constrained yeah I'm I'm going to I'm
going to give you uh and and and
unfortunately have to we have to run in
a couple minutes but I'll just give you
a very quick uh story of what I think is
going on in planaria uh I think uh and
and this is um Steve Steve Frank told me
an interesting analogy to this
apparently uh you know when when raid
arrays became popular right so computer
um computer discs that are that makes it
make copies of themselves so that you
know if something goes wrong he
basically said that when raid erase
became popular the quality of disk media
went down because it wasn't as important
anymore to have to have your Hardware be
super reliable because you've got this
this the system on top of it I think
what what's happened in plaria in that
lineage is that it has uh really uh come
to grips with the fact that the hardware
might be junk and that all the
evolutionary effort went into cranking
the algorithm basically the idea that we
we're going to assume from the beginning
that you're full of mutations you're
unre it's it's unreliable hardware and
we're going to assume it's unreliable
and so what we're going to do is do our
best to have a system that is so highly
regenerative that no matter what's going
on we can we have St a pretty good
chance of making a good planarian the
the the development of plenaria is
called a chaotic mode where it's a total
mess and then it sorts itself out into a
proper worm um I think uh and and and
here's why I think it happened and and
we have computational models that show
that show how this works imagine that
you you have a uh certain competencies
to fix defects for example like in the
Frog we know that if if the mouth is
moved off a little bit in development
it'll soon make its way back to where it
needs to be it's sort of fixed fixes
itself so so in evolution if you have a
system that has a little bit of
Competency to fix itself when that
individual comes up for selection and
selection sees that okay this is a great
individual what selection doesn't know
is is it great because the genome was
amazing or is it great because the
genome was actually so so but it fixed
itself you don't know once you don't
know you're it becomes really difficult
to reward for the best genomes what you
can reward is for the best phenotypic
fitness for the best outcomes and as
soon as you do that that makes the
problem worse because then the
competency goes up then then it becomes
even harder to know what your genome was
so so you so you start off with this
ratchet with this positive feedback loop
and I think in plaria it went all the
way and in another species not so far
and it's some like celegans maybe not at
all but but but that that idea that that
the the more competency of of um uh kind
of uh uh reparative regenerative
developmental process it it it you can
you can eventually if you take it to its
logical conclusion you can say fine
we're going to assume that the that the
structural genome is going to be all
kinds of noise and we're going to come
up with an algorithm that can keep it
clean keep the the morphology clean
assuming that that's assuming that
that's the case and I think plenaria
just like cranked that knob all the way
and salamander sort of do it and and you
know and maybe neems don't do it much
that is very very cool it makes me want
to be a biologist because it the
question if we had more time and I know
we don't is well where on Earth is that
regenerative mechanism coming from if
it's not encoded in the genome somewhere
but we won't go into it it just sounds
to me like there are other ways to
maximize model evidence to use these
active influence words to maximize model
evidence or to return to an attractor
State Beyond genomic stability and
that's really fascinating because I
think people think well the the priors
the So-Cal phenotypic priors are just
what evolution has endowed Us in terms
of our DNA yeah and and and and so if we
wanted to have another discussion this
is where we would talk about xenobots
and anthr robots and these things that
have never been under selection at the
organism level here you know in the
history yeah I mean I've also been I'll
finish up here I've been reading a
little bit of Evan Thompson in mind in
life and he talks about how well the the
autopoetic coupled system is not going
you can't discover that dynamic in the
genome because there are things that are
also selected over time which which
refer to the external Dynamic and which
refer to the world in which we are born
and thrown into and that's really
important as well and I wonder whether
what that interplay means in terms of
regeneration and and morphogenesis but
as as you're all aware and I'm aware
we're Limited in time so we should I'd
absolutely love to do this again I mean
it was absolutely fascinating um guys
thank you uh just if you have a minute
it' be great to know where people can
find your details and also like what you
guys have got coming up in the pipeline
that people can be aware of France you
want to go first sure I mean you can
basically look at our names and and you
know SC and get some of our papers um we
have a great website the for 11 La there
has a bunch bunch of our research come
eliminated um my uh my papers coming up
we actually look in some of these
questions in an anual organism in volvox
that's going to be happening soon I'm
very excited about that uh
because all all the works published for
me right now is a lot of the the
theoretical simulations and talking
about the concepts but I'm excited about
most of my PhD work was trying to apply
this to an organism and see whether or
not there's anything there um so that be
fantastic and Mike yeah so so the lab
website is at uh drmike 11.org one word
drmike 11.org and so that's where all
the peer reviewed stuff the the papers
the protocols um data sets software
everything is is there and then kind of
a little bit more out there some
thoughts are at a Blog called thought
forms. lifee and that's just my that's
just my personal one I'll make sure
everything goes in the uh video
description so people can check it out
there but guys thank you again thank you
so much yeah yeah great conversation
thank you so much thank you it's
pleasure